Preliminary Guide to the Robin William Winks Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robin William Winks papers
1950-2001
MS 336
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
111.75
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, writings,and audiotapes documenting the personal life and professional career of Robin William Winks.
Winks, Robin W., 1930-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robin Winks, pre-1987-1993, 2000, 2001; gift of Avril Winks, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Office files and Miscellaneous recommendations, New Haven Colony Historical Society, Fulbright in Accession 2001-M-019 and all of Accessions 2002-M-011 and 2004-M-060 are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
Biographical / Historical
Robin William Evert Winks was born in Indiana on December 5, 1930. He graduated from the University of Colorado in 1952 and received an M.A. in Maori studies from Victoria University as a Fulbright Scholar in New Zealand. He received his Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins in 1957. Winks joined Yale's history department in 1957, serving as its chairman from 1996 to 1999. From 1999 to 2000, he was the Vyvyan Harmsworth visiting professor of American history at Oxford University. He was a prolific author and in 1987 published Cloak & Gown: Scholars in America's Secret War, an account of the Central Intelligence Agency's relationship with major American universities. Winks died in New Haven, Connecticut, on April 7, 2003.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, writings,and audiotapes documenting the personal life and professional career of Robin William Winks.
Historians; Winks, Robin W., 1930-; Yale University. Department of History
- Inventory
  - Writings, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Microfilms, 1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1987-M-072
  - National Parks Service, 1979-1984 (Box 1–3)
  - Cultural attaché [American Embassy, London, England], 1969-1971 (Box 4–5)
  - Publishers, 1962-1981, undated (Box 6)
  - American Historical Association, 1969-1979, undated (Box 7)
  - Personal correspondence, 1956-1965 (Box 8)
  - Topical files
    - Council on International Exchange of Scholars, 1971-1979, undated (Box 8)
    - Gillomee, Herman, 1968, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Hamden Hall, 1978-1982 (Box 9)
    - Institution for Social Policy Studies (ISPS), 1972-1974 (Box 9)
    - Iran, 1974-1976 (Box 10)
    - Jones, Bartlett C., 1971-1974 (Box 10)
    - Kenyon College, 1967-1975 (Box 10)
    - Peters, Edward, undated (Box 11)
    - Yale Co-operative, 1972-1978 (Box 11)
    - Miscellanea, 1976-1981 (Box 11)
- Additional Material, Accession 1988-M-062
  - Blueprints of the main building at Ellis Island, Statue of Library National Monument, New York/New Jersey, 1983 December 21 (Box 1)
  - Blueprints of the restoration of the Statue of Liberty, prepared for the French-American Committee for Restoration of the Statue of Liberty, Inc., 1983 December 21 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the Statue of Liberty-Ellis Island Centennial Commission, 1983 October 3 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1990-M-072
  - "History of New Haven Parks," as developed by the Parks Board, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1992-M-070
  - A-Am (Box 1)
  - Am-Asia Society (Box 2)
  - Association for Canadian Studies in the United States-Bro (general) (Box 3)
  - Bach-Bolzoni (Box 4)
  - Bonadio-Buxton (Box 5)
  - C (general)-Canadian Consulate (Box 6)
  - Canadian Council-Crick & Alman (Box 7)
  - Crowell-Dushkin Publishing Group (Box 8)
  - E (general)-Eyre Metheun (Box 9)
  - Fa-Go (general) (Box 10)
  - G (general)-Greenwood Press (Box 11)
  - Greenwood Press (cont'd)-Hambly (Box 12)
  - Hanke-Housing (Box 13)
  - Howard-International Student Center (Box 14)
  - Irving-Ko (general) (Box 15)
  - Kahrl-Lamont [governance, Bromley, Dahl, coeducation] (Box 16)
  - Landsberg-Mo (general) (Box 17)
  - Mt. (general)-National Book Awards (Box 18)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities-Oxford University Press (Box 19)
  - Pa (general)-Powell, unidentified (Box 20)
  - Prentice Hall-Reid (Box 21)
  - Research-Saxe (Box 22)
  - Sb-South Africa (Box 23)
  - South Africa 1973-To (Box 24)
  - Tr (general)-Unitd States Information Agency (USIA) (Box 25)
  - Unpublished manuscripts-Wayland Publishers (Box 26)
  - Wesleyan-Yudelman (Box 27)
  - NEH Seminar, 1983-1984 (Box 28)
  - Travelers' Book Society, 1983-1984 (Box 28)
  - Dickinson, A. J., 1986 (Box 28)
  - Colonial History Series (Box 28)
  - Events, 1979-1984 (Box 28)
  - New York Times article, 1987 (Box 28)
  - General letters to 1960 correspondence "closed file", 1954-1960 (Box 28)
  - Manuscripts, writings (Box 29)
  - Publishers' files (Box 30)
  - Publishers/publishing (Box 31)
  - Turnbull, Tulchin, trips (Box 32)
  - Unsorted (Box 32)
  - Articles about Robin Winks (Box 32)
  - Audiocassettes, audiotapes, lectures, [196-]; 1 (Box 32)
  - Committees (Box 33)
  - Bibliographies (Box 33)
  - Lectures (Box 33)
  - Manuscripts, writings (Box 34)
  - Course materials (Box 34)
  - Material on James Grafton Rogers from the Colorado Historical Society, [194-], 1985 (Box 34)
  - Material on Yale Library project from the University of Illinois Archives, [194-], 1985 (Box 34)
  - Yale Student Environmental Coalition, 1991 (Box 34)
  - Reminiscences of a Varied Life [unbound copy of Sherman Kent's autobiography; introduction by Robin W. Winks with accompanying correspondence of Anthony Arnold, Kent's nephew; 3 folders], 1991 (Box 34)
  - "A Title Oscillation: Journal of Comparative Neurology and Psychology, 1904-1910," by Randall D. Wight, Journal of Comparative Neurology, 314:34-36, 1991 (Box 34)
- Additional Material, Accession 1993-M-017
  - Correspondence
    - Primarily postcards of the Winks family [Avril, Honor, Eliot, E. M.], [195-]-[197-], 1990-1991, undated (Box 1)
    - Unsorted, 1961-1991, undated (Box 1)
    - Duke University Press, 1961-1965, undated (Box 1)
    - National Geographic Society, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - Oxford, 1969-1974 (Box 1)
    - Thompson, Tracey, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    - Yale University Press/McGill University Press, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1994-M-026
  - American Studies [videotape], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Robin Winks Discusses Poisoned Pens" [videotape], 1986 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Asian Experiences/American Perspectives" [audiocassette], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "D-Day Deceptions" [audiocassette], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "School/College Collaboration" [audiocassette], 1991 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Military insignia, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-019
  - Oxford History of the British Empire; topical files, [198-]-[199-] (Box 1–4)
  - Correspondence/subject files, [198-]-[1990-] (Box 4)
    - A -C7 (Box 5)
    - A-F (Box 6–7)
    - F-N (Box 8)
    - F (Box 9)
    - H-L (Box 10)
    - L-Z (Box 11)
    - N-W (Box 12)
    - W-Z; miscellaneous correspondence (Box 13)
    - Aa-By (Box 14)
    - B-Da (Box 15)
    - Di-Ha (Box 16)
    - He-Mc (Box 17)
    - Ma-Ta (Box 18)
    - Th-Y (Box 19)
    - D-L (Box 20)
    - L-Su (Box 21)
    - S-Y (Box 22)
  - Office files, Circa 1990s (Box 23–29)
    Conditions Governing Access
    The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  - Miscellaneous recommendations, New Haven Colony Historical Society, Fulbright, [199-] (Box 30)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-011
  - National Parks and Conservation Association [includes reports, board of trustees and executive committee briefing books, correspondence, memoranda, and background files on the National Park Service], 1966-2000 (Box 1–4)
  - National Park Service Act of 1916 [background files, copies of related federal legislation, correspondence, and audio and cassette tapes], 1991-1996 (Box 5–6)
  - Yale University files [re: Studies in the Environment program], 1970s-1990 (Box 7)
  - National Park Service files [correspondence, program proposals, and federal policies] (Box 7)
  - National Park Service [correspondence and publications], 1990s (Box 8)
  - Steamtown National Historic Site, 1995-1998 (Box 8)
  - Underground National Railroad [advisory committee files], 1993-2000 (Box 8)
  - National Parks and Conservation Association [briefing books and correspondence], 1990s (Box 9)
  - Marsh-Billings National Historical Park [publications and brochures], 1993-1999 (Box 9)
  - Marsh-Billings National Historical Park, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 10)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-060
  - Correspondence, 1956-1996 (Box 1)
  - Student papers/essays
    - 1959-2001 (Box 1)
    - 1960s-1998 (Box 2)
    - 1970s-1990s (Box 3)
    - 1970s-1990s (Box 4)
  - Teaching/research files, 1950s-1970s (Box 5–7)
  - Winks's undergraduate lecture notes, 1950s (Box 8–9)
  - Research notes for his unpublished biography of William Francis Drummond Jervois (Box 10–14)
  - Research notes for Cloak & Gown, 1970s-1990s (Box 15–23)
  - Conference presentations and lectures [audio tapes and cassettes], 1970s (Box 24–25)